Anyone who has ever graduated from kindergarten should know the seven foundational data structures
of computer science, which include arrays, link lists, hash tables, stacks, cues, graphs, and trees.
But if you didn't graduate from kindergarten, here's a quick crash course.
A data structure is just a way to organize data in a computer so you can do cred to it efficiently.
Create, read, update, and delete it. In arrays like a row of numbered cubbies,
a linked list is like a treasure map of clues. A hash table is like a locker with your name on it.
A stack is like a stack of books. A queue is like a line of kids at the cafeteria. A graph is
a spider web, and a tree is, well, like a tree. The programming is all about solving problems.
I've got 99 problems, but a data structure ain't one. But for some programmers, data structures
do become a problem. In today's video, we'll look at a few unusual situations where the simple
data structures were not good enough or smart enough to get the job done. Let's start by talking
about the B-tree, not to be confused with a binary tree. One of the most exhilarating things
that ever happened in my life was the first time I implemented a binary search tree,
which prevented my algorithms' time complexity from going burr, turning O of N squared into a
much faster O of log N. But binary search trees have one problem. Each node in the tree can only
have two children, which means the depth of the tree grows rapidly, and doesn't scale very
well for things like modern hard drives with massive amounts of data to search through. To address
this problem a long time ago, programmers at Boeing developed the self-balancing tree or B-tree.
Although nowadays you'll mostly find B-plus trees and file systems and databases.
At a high level, what makes them special is that each node can have multiple children of
sorted keys. These are called internal nodes, and they work like signposts, that point to leaf
nodes that hold the actual data, or pointers to data. So it works kind of like a binary tree,
but greatly reduces the disk IO operations by cutting down the height of the tree, which is pretty
cool, but there are many other types of trees in nature and in computers, like the radix tree.
Like there are billions of IP addresses in the world, but have you ever wondered how computers
wrap between them so efficiently to make the internet work. A radix tree is special because
nodes with only one child are emerged with their parent, and that makes them highly efficient when
finding values with a shared prefix, like an IP address. For example, if I made a tree to find
words that start with C, our tree might look like this, but in a radix tree we can reduce the depth
by emerging the last child. That's ideal when you have many shared prefixes, but doesn't work
so well with big complex strings, like all the vibe coded slots you're trying to debug in your
IDE right now. A rope is yet another type of tree that breaks down strings into manageable chunks.
Instead of one continuous strand, you cut it into many smaller manageable segments,
then you tie these segments together using smaller knots that also tell you how long each segment
they represent is. This allows tools like text editors to more efficiently modify large documents,
but in some cases figuring out what not to search is more important, and that's where bloom filters
come in. It's a probabilistic data structure that can tell you if an item is definitely not
in a set, or maybe is in a set. It works by using multiple hash functions to set and check bits in
a fixed sized array, allowing fast membership tests with possible false positives, but no false
negatives. It's like a balancer to club who always knows exactly who to kick out. One of the
weirdest things in nature though is the cuckoo bird. A bird that sneaks into another bird's nest
and replaces its eggs with its own. Tricking the hose to incubate and care for the cuckoo check.
This behavior not only inspired the term cuckled, but also cuckoo hashing and programming.
According to my wife's boyfriend, it's a collision resolution technique where each key in a
hash table has two or more possible positions, and if one spot is taken, the existing key is kicked out
like a cuckoo, and reinserted in an alternate location. The end result is constant time worst case
complexity for lookups, which is as fast as you can possibly go when it comes to algorithms. But if
you want to optimize your own code with these weird data structures, you need to know about code
rabbit, the sponsor of today's video. They just released a new VS Code extension that gives you
advanced code reviews right in your editor, so you can catch the majority of bugs before you even
submit a pull request. Unlike other tools, the extension understands the context of your entire
code base, allowing it to catch more bugs, like all the AI slop your favorite code gen tool left
behind. It gives you line-by-line comments on all issues, so you can see it reasoning, then it
offers simple one-click fixes to help you clean things up quickly. The code rabbit is free to
use in the IDE and work seamlessly with VS Code as well as forks like cursor and wind serve.
It download the extension using the link below to try it out. Thanks for watching, and I will see you
in the next one.